Guide to the James P. Sullivan Collection AIA.048
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
James P. Sullivan Collection
1905-1908
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Archives of Irish America
AIA.048
0.25 Linear Feet (1 CD - 56 digital images from scrapbook)
James P. Sullivan was the third of six children born to Irish immigrants Jeremiah Sullivan, a grocer, and his wife Elizabeth Flynn Sullivan. Young J.P., or Jim, was born on February 28, 1885 and spent his early years in Manhattan where he attended P.S. 14 on East 27th Street and joined the track team of the St. Bartholomew Boys Club and, later, of the 22nd Regiment. By that time, six foot tall Jim could run a mile in 4:50. In September 1905 at the New York Metro Senior American Athletic Union Championships, Sullivan ran the mile in 4:22 creating a new American record. After impressive showings at the Canadian Championships and the New York Athletic Club Games that same month, he became known in the press as "4:22 Jim" and by March 1906 had been selected for the American Olympic team. The collection consists of items from the Sullivan family scrapbook. Included are photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondence and membership cards for the Irish-American Athletic Club.
Provenance
All images are from James P. Sullivan's scrapbook, loaned for to the Archives of Irish America, New York University, by his grandsons Brian and Terry Sullivan.
The images were used for an online exhibit. The collection consists of 56 digital images.
Originals were returned to the family.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged into one series in the order items appear on the CD.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
The collection consists of items from the Sullivan family scrapbook. Included are photographs, newspaper clippings, correspondence and membership cards for the Irish-American Athletic Club. Also part of this collection is the Mecca Cigarette card with Sullivan's image as part of the Mecca Cigarette Champion Athlete and Prize Fighter Series.
Images are available for viewing in a Flikr exhibit at http://www.flickr.com/photos/27630285@N07/3240069844/in/set-72157613167342984/. A copy of the images is also available in the Archives on a Cd-Rom.
Historical/Biographical Note
James Paul [sometimes listed as Patrick] Sullivan was the third of six surviving children born to Irish immigrants Jeremiah Sullivan, a grocer, and his wife Elizabeth Flynn, who arrived in the United States in 1870 and 1875 respectively. Young J.P., or Jim, was born on February 28, 1885 and spent his early years in Manhattan where he attended P.S. 14 on East 27th Street and joined the track team of the St. Bartholomew Boys Club and, later, of the 22nd Regiment. By that time, six foot tall Jim could run a mile in 4:50. In September 1905 at the New York Metro Senior American Athletic Union Championships, Sullivan ran the mile in 4:22 creating a new American record. After impressive showings at the Canadian Championships and the New York Athletic Club Games that same month, he became known in the press as "4:22 Jim" and by March 1906 had been selected for the American Olympic team.
Athens, Greece was the site for a special international athletic meeting known as the Intercalated Games scheduled between the 1904 and 1908 Olympic years. The American Olympic team sailed from New York City on the S.S. Barbarosa on 31 March 1906 with James P. Sullivan aboard, on leave from his position as a junior clerk with the Department of Education's Bureau of Buildings.
In Athens, Sullivan competed in the 800 meter race but did not qualify for the final. He also ran in the 1500 meter race, finishing fifth. His second place win at the Olympic Trials in Philadelphia in June 1908 made him one of thirteen members of the Irish American Athletic Club selected to represent the United States at the 1908 Olympic Games in London.
But, once again, Jim Sullivan did not bring home an Olympic medal. Nevertheless, he was part of an historic track-and-field team competing under the American flag – IAAC teammates Martin Sheridan, John J. Hayes, and Mel Sheppard, for example, brought home the gold in discus throw, Greek discus, the marathon, and the 1500 meter respectively – a team that was fêted upon their return to New York with a parade down Fifth Avenue and a reception at Sagamore Hill on Long Island with President Theodore Roosevelt.
Jim Sullivan continued running competitively until 1912, despite surgery for a tendon injury and times for the mile – like 4:24 or 4:29 – that never beat his personal best. In 1910 and 1911 his image was selected for two series of tobacco cards (Hassan and Mecca) featuring Champion Athletes and Prizefighters.
He married Grace Burke in 1913 – the daughter of Irish immigrants, Richard (a broker at the Custom House) and Mary – and they raised two children, Richard and Elise, on his job as a clerk for the Kings County Court, a position he held until 1958. James P. Sullivan died on 9 April 1965 at age 79.
Digital images.; Irish Americans -- Societies, etc.; Correspondence.; Articles.; Olympics.; Black-and-white photographs.; Cigarette cards.; Sullivan, James P., 1885-1965; Irish American Athletic Club
- Inventory
  - Newspaper Clipping: 4:22 Sullivan "One Record by Which Sullivan is Alone", circa 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_001)
  - Photograph: J.P. Sullivan, Track Captain 13th Artillery AC, undated (Box 1, Item aia048_002)
  - 1900 Census - 12th Census of the United States, New York County: Page with Sullivan Family information (Box 1, Item aia048_003)
  - Newspaper clipping: "Finish of the One Mile Run J.P. Sullivan 1st, Harvey W. Cohn 2nd, 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_004)
  - Letter from American Committee of the Olympian Games at Athens Greece regarding 1906 games, informing Sullivan he was chosen unanimously to represent the United States; first page only, Mar 8 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_005)
  - 1910 Census - 13th Census of the United States, Kings County, Sullivan Family information, 1 page (Box 1, Item aia048_006)
  - Photograph: James Sullivan at Acroplis, Athens with two unidentified men, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_007)
  - Photograph: James Sullivan at the Porch of the Maidens, the Acroplis, Athens, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_008)
  - Newpaper clippings: The [Globe and Commercial] Advertiser, New York "Olympic Stars Peform To-Day at Celtic Park", Sep 7, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_009)
  - Cartoon "Uncle to the Fore!" by J. Campbell Cory, unidentified publication, Apr 27, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_010)
  - Cigarette Card: James P. Sullivan, color; Mecca Cigarettes Champion Athlete and Prize Fighter Series, circa 1911 (Box 1, Item aia048_011)
  - Cigarette Card Verso: James P. Sullivan, color; Mecca Cigarettes Champion Athlete and Prize Fighter Series; contains biographical and competition information on Sullivan, circa 1911 (Box 1, Item aia048_012)
  - Newpaper clipping: "Irish Heroes of Olympia Honored at Great Feast", unidentified source, Sep 22, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_013)
  - Military Honorable Discharge document from the State of New York to James Sullivan, Nov 25, 1910 (Box 1, Item aia048_014)
  - Newspaper Clipping: "Marathon Winner Gets Big Welcome", Aug 20, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_015)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Document: "One Year's Record of the Irish-American Athletic Club", circa 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_015)
  - Irish American Atheltic Club Document: "Winners of National Championship at St. Louis Exposition", circa 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_016)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Photograph: Group, circa 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_017)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Membership Card, 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_019)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Membership Card, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_020)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Membership Card: Verso, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_021)
  - Irish American Athletic Club Membership Card, 1909 (Box 1, Item aia048_022)
  - Newspaper Clipping: "Irish-Americans Lead World in Athletic Skills"; unidentified source, part 1, undated (Box 1, Item aia048_023)
  - Newspaper Clipping: "Irish-Americans Lead World in Athletic Skills"; unidentified source, part 2, undated (Box 1, Item aia048_024)
  - Photograph: J.P. Sullivan, undated (Box 1, Item aia048_025)
  - Letter: from Meyer to Sullivan, page 1, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_026)
  - Letter: from Meyer to Sullivan, page 2, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_027)
  - Letter: from Meyer to Sullivan, page 2 (additional image), 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_028)
  - Newspaper clipping, fragment: Story about the IACC, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_029)
  - Newspaper clipping "Will Decorate City in Honor of Athletes", 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_030)
  - Newspaper clipping: New York American "Irish Club Defeats the New York A.C., 87 to 48", Aug 27, 1907 (Box 1, Item aia048_031)
  - Newspaper clipping: New York Herald "Yankee Athletes Triumph Abr[oad]", Jul 14, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_032)
  - Newspaper clipping: New York Press "Training-Camp Life of the Men Who Battle for the Winged Fist" page 1, Jul 14, 1907 (Box 1, Item aia048_033)
  - Newspaper clipping: New York Press "Training-Camp Life of the Men Who Battle for the Winged Fist" page 2, Jul 14, 1907 (Box 1, Item aia048_034)
  - Picture, New York [City] Parade "The Athletes Come Down Fifth Avenue in Automobiles Preceded by the Marathon Trophy on a Float", 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_035)
  - Newspaper clipping, fragment: New York Times "Pay Final Tribute to Victors", Sep 22, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_036)
  - Certificate Olympic Games 1908: James Sullivan placed 2nd in 1500 meter trials (Box 1, Item aia048_037)
  - Newspaper clipping: New York Press "Crack Distance Runners of Irish-American A.C."; depicts Harvey W. Cohn and James P. Sullivan, Jan 7, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_038)
  - Letter, Department of Correction Commissioner, John Coggey to Egerton L. Winthrop, Jr., President Board of Education offer to give James Sullivan a raise, Jun 29, 1907 (Box 1, Item aia048_039)
  - [Minutes?] Department of Education noting James Sullivans request of leave from his position to participate in the 1906 Olympics (granted), Mar 26, 1906 (Box 1, Item aia048_040)
  - Correspondence: Paul Thompason, Manager, The Article Synidcate to J.P. Sullivan, Esq. Irish-Americna Athletic Club requesting photograph of Sullivan, Jun 9, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_041)
  - Article: Running Times "4:22 Jim" page 1 of 3, Dec 1985 (Box 1, Item aia048_042)
  - Article: Running Times "4:22 Jim" page 2 of 3, Dec 1985 (Box 1, Item aia048_043)
  - Article: Running Times "4:22 Jim" page 3 of 3, Dec 1985 (Box 1, Item aia048_044)
  - Picture: Sagamore Hill 1908 with headline "The Athletes Coming Down Fifth Avenue...." (Box 1, Item aia048_045)
  - Newspaper clipping, fragment: Sullivan interview 1958 "U.S. First No. 1 Miler Still Keeps in Shape" (Box 1, Item aia048_046)
  - Article and picture of Sullivan running "Athletes who Race at 22nd Regiment Armory To-night" Pictured: Cohen, Banderman, Sullivan and Freeman, circa 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_047)
  - Photograph: Sullivan in a race, circa 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_048)
  - Newspaper clipping: The Globe and Commercial Advertiser, New York "Olympic Stars Perform To-Day at Celtic Park", undated (Box 1, Item aia048_049)
  - Page from The Graphi c "American Triumps at the Olympic Games" p. 1, Jul 25, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_050)
  - Page from The Graphic "American Triumps at the Olympic Games" p. 2, Jul 25, 1909 (Box 1, Item aia048_051)
  - Newspaper clipping: The Sun "Col. Roosevelt as He Appeared When He Greeted Olympic Team", Sep 1, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_052)
  - Newspaper clipping The World "Olympic Team Chosen, They're World Beaters" p. 1, Jun 9, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_053)
  - Newspaper clipping The World "Olympic Team Chosen, They're World Beaters" p. 2, Jun 9, 1908 (Box 1, Item aia048_054)
  - Newspaper clipping fragment, The World, Pictures of Melvin Shephard and Jas. P. Sullivan, Jan 25, 1912 (Box 1, Item aia048_055)
  - Photograph: Winning Mile, circa 1905 (Box 1, Item aia048_056)